A Guide to the James Branch Cabell Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7779-b
James Branch Cabell Collection 1886-1928
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7779-b
10 bound volumes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1966 May 4
Item Listing
These scrapbooks are also on microfilm (M-1708-1710). The letters listed are in the approximate order in which they appear in the scrapbook.
  Scrapbook 1
- Scrapbook 1, 1904-1909
  Clippings, re: James Branch Cabell and his works, chiefly reviews of his early books, with some letters, listed below; 60 pp.
  - Henry W. Lanier to James Branch Cabell, 1906 Jun 7; TLS, 2 p.
  - Justus Miles Forman to James Branch Cabell, 1904 Oct 13; ALS, 5 p.
  - Poem beginning, "Down by the river..., 1911 Jul 11; AMs, 3 p.
    [presumably by James Branch Cabell, in unknown hand.]
  - Merle Johnson to James Branch Cabell, n.d.; ALS, 4 p.
  - Walter H[ines] Page to James Branch Cabell, 1906 Jun 8; TLS, 2 p.
  - Gilman Hall to James Branch Cabell, n.y. Jan 23; ALS, 3 p.
  - H[enry] M[ills] Alden to James Branch Cabell, 1904 Mar 29; ALS, 1 p.
  - Katherine Hilliard Young to James Branch Cabell, n.y. Apr 23; ALS, 2 p.
  - Mrs. M. [Leapour] to James Branch Cabell, 1908 Jan 24; ALS, 3 p.
  - David A. Ross to James Branch Cabell, 1908 May 18; ALS, 2 p.
  - Joseph Neuhan to James Branch Cabell, 1904 Sep 29; ALS, 1 p.
  - W. R. Bingham to James Branch Cabell, 1911 Mar 9; ALS, 2 p.
  - John J. [Myres] to James Branch Cabell, 1908 Sep 14; ALS, 2 p.
  - M. L. Minney to James Branch Cabell, n.y. Aug 7; ALS, 1 p.
  - [N. Néonard] to [ James Branch Cabell], 1907 Dec 6; ALS, 1 p.
  - F. B. Luquiens to James Branch Cabell, 1908 Apr 14; ALS, 2 p.
  - F. B. Luquiens to James Branch Cabell, 1908 May 17; ALS, 2 p.
  - Staunton Hynes to Editor, Harpers Monthly, 1904 Oct 8; ALS, 2 p.
  - Henry W. Lanier to James Branch Cabell, 1908 Jul 25; TLS, 1 p.
  - R[ichard] H[arding] Davis to Henry W. Lanier, 1908 Aug 21; TLS, 1 p.
  - L. Rix Babbitt to James Branch Cabell, n.d.; ALS, 8 p.
  - Miss J. S. Roberts to James Branch Cabell, Dec 16; ALS, 8 p.
  Scrapbook 2
- Scrapbook 2, 1886-1919
  Clippings, manuscripts, re:
  The Soul of Melicent
  ,
  The Cream of the Jest
  Beyond Life
  , with some letters, listed below, 104 p.
  - Manuscript beginning, "I don't like human beings,' he had said", n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
  - H[ans] R[udolph] R[einhard] Hertzberg to James Branch Cabell, 1913 Oct 13; ALS, 2 p.
  - Edward R. Schauffler to James Branch Cabell, 1913 Oct 14; TLS, 2 p.
  - Daniel E. Hervey to [ James Branch Cabell], 1913 Oct 16; ALS, 1 p.
  - "The Wonderful Cat" by James Branch Cabell, 1886 [May or June]; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Anna Hempstead Branch to James Branch Cabell, 1905 Aug 11; ALS, 4 p.
  - [ W. D. Mann] to James Branch Cabell, 1907 Jan 4; TLS, 1 p.
  - Elinor Macartney Lane to James Branch Cabell, n.d.; ALS, 3 p.
  - Walter H[ines] Page to James Branch Cabell, 1913 Apr 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine to James Branch Cabell, w/envelope, [1911] Oct 18; ALS, 5 p.
  - Albert Bigelow Paine to James Branch Cabell, w/envelope, [1911] Nov 10; ALS, 3 p.
  - Theodore Roosevelt to James Branch Cabell, 1905 Oct 21; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edmund M. Ashe to James Branch Cabell, 1903 May 4; ALS, 3 p.
  - Belle Radcliffe Lannock to James Branch Cabell, w/envelope, 1917 Jul 3; ALS, 6 p.
  - J. B. Lippincott Co. to James Branch Cabell, 1915 Feb 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - William Loeb, Jr. to James Branch Cabell, n.d.; Telegram
  - Title pages and note from The Cream of the Jest, 1916 Oct; TMs, 2 p.
  - S[amuel] Foster Damon to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Mar 28; TLS, 2 p.
  - H. L. Mencken to James Branch Cabell, [1917]; TNS, 1 p.
  - Lewis H. Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1917 Nov 24; TLS, 1 p.
  - Lewis H. Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1918 Jan 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - Lewis H. Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1918 Feb 3; TLS, 2 p.
  - Vincent Starrett to James Branch Cabell, 1917 Dec 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - Sinclair Lewis to James Branch Cabell, w/envelope, [1911] Nov 12; ALS, 9 p.
  - Burton Rascoe to James Branch Cabell, 1917 [Dec 31]; TLS, 2 p.
  - Leslie Reed to James Branch Cabell, 1918 Feb 3; ALS, 4 p.
  - Burton [Rascoe] to Guy [Holt], [1918]; TN, 1 p.
    [copy for James Branch Cabell]
  - Roads from Reality, n.d.; AM, 1 p.
  - Harold Ward to James Branch Cabell, 1918 Nov 16; TLS, 2 p.
  - Vincent Starrett to James Branch Cabell, 1918 May 10; ALS, 1 p.
  - Wilson Follett to James Branch Cabell, 1918 May 7; TLS, 2 p.
  - Harold Ward("Stéphane Boecklin") to James Branch Cabell, 1918 Jun 5; TLS, 2 p.
  - Review of The Cream of the Jest by [ Harold Ward], [1918]; TMs, 4 p.
  - Notes, titled "Beyond Words", 1918 Apr 13; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Review of The Cream of the Jest by [ Harold Ward] (carbon), 1918 Aug 5; TMs, 6 p.
  - [Excerpt from The Cream of the Jest ] beginning, "Charteris. That tenet comes with queer grace from you...," w/auto. corrections, [1918]; TMs, 1 p.
  - Essay beginning, "..privileged to witness corrections the world-wide failure of Christianity...," w/auto. corrections, [1918]; TMs, 4 p.
  - Pages 174-175 of [a novel] beginning,"...from conceding our destinies in any way....," w/auto. corrections, [1918]; TMs, 2 p.
  - Joseph A. Margolis to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Feb 18; ALS, 2 p.
  - Carl Van Vechten to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Mar 11; TLS, 1 p.
  - B. J. Scannell to Robert M. McBride and Co.(trans.), 1919 Mar 7; TL, 1 p.
  - [N. C.] Baldwin to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Feb 12; TLS, 1 p.
  - Review of Beyond Life by Dorothy Scarborough, [1918]; TMs, 7 p.
  - A. L. S. Wood to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Mar 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - Harold Ward to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Jan 9; TLS, 3 p.
  - Floyd Dell to James Branch Cabell, [1919]; ALS, 4 p.
  - William Rose Benét to James Branch Cabell, 1919 May 21; TLS, 2 p.
  - Lewis Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Mar 1; ALS, 5 p.
  - Lewis Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Apr 24; ALS, 3 p.
  - H. L. Mencken to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Feb 17; TLS, 2 p.
  - H. L. Mencken to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Jan 10; TLS, 1 p.
  - Henry B. Fuller to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Mar 17; ALS, 2 p.
  - Henry B. Fuller to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Apr 12; ALS, 4 p.
  - T. Swann Harding to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Jun 3; TLS, 1 p.
  - Joseph Hergesheimer to [Benjamin Floyer] Glazer(carbon), [1919]; TLS, 2 p.
  - Henry A. Lappin to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Apr 10; ALS, 4 p.
  - Henry A. Lappin to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Apr 4; ALS, 1 p.
  Scrapbook 3
- Scrapbook 3, 1919-1920
  Clippings, proofs of advertisements, re:
  Jurgen
  , with some letters listed below, 93 p.
  - Dorothy Scarborough to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Sep 23; TLS, 2 p.
  - Lucien Dean Pearson to James Branch Cabell, [1919]; ALS, 3 p.
  - James Branch Cabell at work at his desk, [1919]; Photo
  - Grace Hegger Lewis to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Oct 27; TLS, 2 p.
  - Sinclair Lewis to James Branch Cabell, [1919]; TLS, 1 p.
  - Paul Jordan Smith to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Oct 24; ALS, 3 p.
  - Harold Ward to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Oct 30; TLS, 1 p.
  - Aleister Crowley to James Branch vCabell, [1919]; ANS, 1 p.
  - Aleister Crowley to James Branch Cabell, w/encl. TMs (carbon), 6 p., of review of Jurgen by Trowley, 1919 Oct 29; TLS, 1 p.
  - F. [Batcher] to Guy [Holt], [1919]; ALS, 1 p.
  - Review of Jurgen by Ben Hecht, [1919]; TMsS, 1 p.
  - Henry [Sell] to Guy [Holt], [1919]; ANS, 1 p.
  - John R. Reinhard to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Dec 19; TLS, 1 p.
  - Benjamin Glazer to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Oct 22; TLS, 1 p.
  - Joseph Hergesheimer to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Sep 30; TLS, 2 p.
  - Review of Jurgen, by Joseph Hergesheimer, 1919 Sep 29; TMsS, 3 p.
  - H. [Broford] James to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Jan 22; TLS, 1 p.
  - Francis Rolt-Wheeler to [ James Branch Cabell], 1919 Dec 16; TLS, 1 p.
  - E. Wetmore to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Jan 12; ALS, 4 p.
  - E. Wetmore to James Branch Cabell, [1919] Jan 24; ALS, 3 p.
  - Edward J. O'Brien to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Sep 23; TLS, 1 p.
  - Society of Arts and Sciences to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 21; Telegram
  - Edward [Coyle] to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Oct 18; ALS, 1 p.
  - Gilbert Cannan to [Guy] Holt(carbon), 1919 Dec 15; TL, 1 p.
  - William Rose Benét to James Branch Cabell, [1919]; ALS, 2 p.
  - Charles C. Baldwin to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Dec 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - Guy Holt to Hugh Walpole(trans.), 1919 Oct 31; TL, 1 p.
  - Hugh Walpole to [ Guy Holt] (carbon), 1919 Nov 7; TL, 1 p.
  - Statement by Sinclair Lewis about Jurgen (carbon), [1919]; TMs, 1 p.
  - H. E. [Dounce] to [Guy] Holt, 1919 Dec 23; TLS, 1 p.
  - Margaret Babcock to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Oct 26; ALS, 3 p.
  - Arington H. Carman to James Branch Cabell, w/encl. 1 p. transcript of ALS, J. E. Baskerville to Carman, 1920 Feb 16; ALS, 2 p.
  - J. D. Chamberlain to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 26; ALS, 1 p.
  - Fred[erick] R. Ashfield to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Dec 29; TLS, 1 p.
  - Wilson Follett to James Branch Cabell, 1919 [Nov]; TLS, 5 p.
  - Review of Jurgen by Wilson Follett(carbon), [1919]; TMs, 2 p.
  - Louis Untermeyer to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 26; TLS, 1 p.
  - Review of Jurgen by Henry A. Lappin, [1920 Jan]; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Gideon Timberlake to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 21; TLS, 2 p.
  - Gideon Timberlake to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 22; TLS, 1 p.
  - Harold Ward to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 7; TLS, 1 p.
  - Benjamin De Casseres to James Branch Cabell, [1920 Jan]; ALS, 2 p.
  - Margaret Lee to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Nov 28; TLS, 1 p.
  - Margaret Lee to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Nov 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - H. L. Mencken to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Nov 14; TLS, 1 p.
  - Mrs. [M. P.] Branch to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 19; ALS, 3 p.
  - Harold Davis to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 7; ALS, 2 p.
  - Pierre Troubetzkoy to James Branch Cabell, [1920] Feb 19; ALS, 2 p.
  - Article, re: suppression of Jurgen (carbon), 1920 Jan 15; TMs, 2 p.
  - Eleanor Blake Atkinson to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 12; ALS, 6 p.
  - Margaret Lee to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jan 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - T. [N.] Smith to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 13; TLS, 1 p.
  - George T. Keating to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 2; TLS, 1 p.
  - Unknown to Mr. and Mrs. Solle, 1919 Dec 14; TL, 1 p.
  - Ernest A. Boyd to [Guy] Holt(trans.), 1920 Feb 10; TL, 2 p.
  - Charles J. Finger to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 22; TLS, 1 p.
  - Charles J. Finger to James Branch Cabell, 1919 Dec 12; TLS, 1 p.
  - Samuel Barlow to James Branch Cabell, [1920] Feb 24; TLS, 1 p.
  - Samuel L. Barlow to James Branch Cabell, [1920] Mar; TLS, 1 p.
  - John A. Ten Eyck III, 1920 Feb 22; ALS, 2 p.
  - Charles S. Vial to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Mar 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - John Cornell to James Branch vCabell, 1920 Mar 12; TLS, 1 p.
  - Isaac Goldberg to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Apr 19; TLS, 1 p.
  - Article defending Jurgen by A. Z. Lopez-Penha in Spanish (trans.), 1920 Mar 24; TMs, 1 p.
  - Emergency Committee to Sir or Madam, 1920 Feb 13; TL, 1 p.
    [re: Jurgen, w/encl. a 1 p. protest] (reproduced)
  - Paul Jordan Smith to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Feb 27; ALS, 5 p.
  - Thomas Edgelow to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Mar 27; TLS, 1 p.
  - Alyce M. Fletcher to James Branch Cabell, encl. 5 p. TMs, review of Jurgen, 1920 May 11; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edwin J. Mayer to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jun 22; TLS, 2 p.
  - Helen McAfee to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jul 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - Ralph F. Holmes to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jul 9; TLS, 1 p.
  - Russell Gore to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Jul 8; TLS, 1 p.
  - "In the Matter of Jurgen " by Guy Holt(carbon), [1920]; TMs, 4 p.
  - Benjamin De Casseres to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; TLS, 1 p.
  - Basil Thompson to James Branch Cabell, w/auto. 2nd page, [1920] Sep 3; TLS, 2 p.
  - Basil Thompson to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Sep 3; ALS, 2 p.
  - Charles Dexter Allen to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Mar 21; ALS, 3 p.
  - Thomas [W.] Duffy to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Apr 16; TLS, 1 p.
  - Milka Davenport Moss to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Apr 6; ALS, 3 p.
  - Gregory Stragnell to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Aug 3; ALS, 2 p.
  - Roy L. McCardell to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Aug 9; TLS, 1 p.
  - Roy L. McCardell to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Aug 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - Walter Adolphe Roberts to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Apr 29; TLS, 2 p.
  - [ Wilbur Cross] to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Mar 2; TLS, 1 p.
  - Charles Ridgely to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Mar 2; ALS, 2 p.
  - Marion A. Smith to James Branch Cabell, 1920 May 21; TLS, 3 p.
  - B[ernard] K[eble] Sandwell to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Aug 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - Marion Nelson Waldrip to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; TLS, 1 p.
  - G. A. Van Nosdall to James Branch Cabell, 1920 May 10; TLS, 1 p.
  Scrapbook 4
- Scrapbook 4, 1920-1921
  Clippings re:
  Domnei
  The Cords of Vanity
  - George Moore to Barrett H. Clark(trans.), 1920 Sep 10; TL, 1 p.
  - Kate D[ouglas] [Wiggin] to Emergency Committee (carbon), 1920 Feb 17; TL, 1 p.
  - E[ugene] F[rancis] Saxton to Barrett H. Clark(carbon), 1920 Feb 28; TL, 1 p.
  - James Branch Cabell to Edward Hale Bierstadt(carbon), 1920 Feb 17; TL, 1 p.
  - [ E. Paxton] to James Branch Cabell, w/auto. postscript, 1920 Sep 16; TLS, 1 p.
  - L. W. Neustadler to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Oct 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - John M. Hill to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Oct 22; TLS, 2 p.
  - Margaret Donnan to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Oct 31; TLS, 2 p.
  - Arthur E. Becher to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Sep 24; ALS, 1 p.
  - Frances Newman to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; ALS, 2 p.
  - Anne Rutherfoord Wayland to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 4; ALS, 3 p.
  - Alice Wade Mulhern to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 11; ALS, 2 p.
  - Leonard D. Weil to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; ALS, 1 p.
  - Anne Rutherfoord Wayland to James Branch Cabell, in form of poem, 1920 Aug 7; ALS, 2 p.
  - Maynard D. Follin to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Oct 5; ALS, 2 p.
  - Lewis Galantière to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Sep 29; ALS, 2 p.
  - William Kavanaugh Doty to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 13; TLS, 2 p.
  - Vincent Starrett to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Oct 1; ALS, 2 p.
  - Merle Johnson to James Branch Cabell, w/drawing on paper, 1920 Nov 23; ALS, 2 p.
  - Robert Nathan to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; ALS, 2 p.
  - Robert C. Holliday to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 3; ALS, 2 p.
  - Frederick Ebell Fiske to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 27; ALS, 4 p.
  - Lucien Dean Pearson to James Branch Cabell, [1920]; ALS, 4 p.
  - Harry Turner to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 27; TLS, 1 p.
  - Henry B. Flarsheim to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 19; TLS, 1 p.
  - Kingsland Spencer to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 7; ALS, 2 p.
  - Kingsland Spencer to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Nov 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Springtime in Town" by Kingsland Spencer, 1917 Jun 5; TMsS, 1 p.
  - John J. Gunther to James Branch Cabell, encl. 16 pp. TMs essay on James Branch Cabell: "James Branch Cabell: An Introduction" by Gunther, 1920 May 31; ALS, 2 p.
  - E. Goodhue to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 2; ALS, 1 p.
  - Deems Taylor to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 24; ALS, 2 p.
  - J. T. Stewart to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 10; ALS, 1 p.
  - Olga R. Moore to James Branch Cabell, [1920] Dec 6; ALS, 3 p.
  - Ethel M. Kelley to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 27; ALS, 2 p.
  - Merle Johnson to [ James Branch Cabell], 1920 Dec 29; ANS, 1 p.
  - Harold Ward to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - Essay, "The Unknown Poetry of James Branch Cabell" by Louis Untermeyer(carbon), [1920]; AMsS, 5 p.
  - Louise H. Guyol to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jan 10; ALS, 3 p.
  - Elisabeth Grinnell to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Jan 16; ALS, 3 p.
  - Lee B. Mihan to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jan 10; TLS, 6 p.
  - George A. Van Nosdall to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jan 21; TLS, 2 p.
  - George A. Van Nosdall, 1921 Jan 30; TLS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "The Hashish-Eater," inscribed by Clark Ashton Smith to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; TMsS, 12 p.
  - Dorothea Lawrance Mann to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 19; ALS, 3 p.
  - Dorothea Lawrance Mann to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Feb 13; ALS, 4 p.
  - Woodward Lee Carter to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jan 22; ALS, 3 p.
  - William R. Anderson to James Branch Cabell, 1920 Dec 28; TLS, 1 p.
  - Deems Taylor to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jan 5; TLS, 2 p.
  - H[enry] W[alcott] Boynton to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Feb 2; TLS, 1 p.
  - Leo B. Mihan to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Feb 8; TLS, 1 p.
  - Berthe Grunbaum to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Feb 23; ALS, 4 p.
  - William Gamalial [Shegard] to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Feb 20; ALS, 2 p.
  - Helen A. Seyffert to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Feb 23; ALS, 3 p.
  - Helen A. Seyffert to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; ALS, 3 p.
  - Evelyn Dewey Miller to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; TLS, 6 p.
  - Mary Byerley to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 13; ALS, 3 p.
  - Whitelaw Saunders to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 14; TLS, 1 p.
  - T. [N.] Smith to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Mar 7; ALS, 1 p.
  - Blanche Colton Williams to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 13; TLS, 1 p.
  - Deems Taylor to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 10; TLS, 1 p.
  - Frances Newman to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; TLS, 1 p.
  - Dorothy Scarborough to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 17; TLS, 2 p.
  - Donald Ogden Stewart to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Mar 19; ALS, 2 p.
  - Valerie de Milhau to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 22; ALS, 2 p.
  - Carl Van Doren to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 17; TLS, 1 p.
  - H. L. Mencken to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 26; TLS, 1 p.
  - Oswald Brod to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 28; ALS, 1 p.
  - Basil Thompson to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 30; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edward Hale Bierstadt to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 25; TLS, 1 p.
  - William J. Cobwin to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Apr 4; ALS, 4 p.
  - Morris Fishbein to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 31; TLS, 1p.
  - Rosanna Elizabeth Roe to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 12; ALS, 5 p.
  - Joseph A. Margolis to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - John A. Thomas to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - Harold Goddard Rugg to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - Oswald Brod to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 1; ALS, 1 p.
  - Charles Bayly, Jr. to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 7; ALS, 3 p.
  - B. Russell Herts to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Apr 11; ALS, 3 p.
  - Dorothea Lawrance Mann to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - Don Bregenzer to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - M. Kathryn Spiers to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - Mary Brecht Pulver to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - Jerome E. Brooks to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 27; TLS, 2 p.
  - William R. A. Hays to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 17; ALS, 2 p.
  - William R. A. Hays to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 25; TLS, 1 p.
  - Carlton A. Talbott to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - Bernice Stewart to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 10; ALS, 3 p.
  - Irma Kennard to Editor of New York Times Book Review, 1921 Feb 23; TLS, 1 p.
  - Charles Roberts Seabrook to Robert McBride and Co., encl. 2 pp. TLS, May 5, Seabrook to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 5; TLS, 1 p.
  - Willard S. Morse to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 18; ALS, 2 p.
  - Nathan Van Patten to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 15; ALS, 1 p.
  - William R. A. Hays to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 22; ALS, 2 p.
  - Mary Brecht Pulver to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Apr 29; ALS, 2 p.
  - Mrs. C. H. McDonald to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 18; ALS, 4 p.
  - Frederick B. Eddy to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 20; TLS, 3 p.
  - Henry S[eidel] Canby to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 26; TLS, 1 p.
  - Ben Ray Redman to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Apr 30; TLS, 2 p.
  - H. B. Fuller to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 10; ALS, 2 p.
  - Edward Hale Bierstadt to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 4; TLS, 2 p.
  - George T. Keating to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 11; TLS, 1 p.
  - Margaret Lee to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edward Hale Bierstadt to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 23; TLS, 1 p.
  - Morris Fishbein to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 24; TLS, 1 p.
  - Bernhardt Wall to James Branch Cabell, 1920 May 7; ALS, 2 p.
  - Sadie B. Goodman to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 9; TL, 1 p.
  - Thomas A. Boyd to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 1; TLS, 1 p.
  - John Peale Bishop to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - Frank Crowninshield to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 13; TLS, 1 p.
  - Virginia MacFadyen to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 1; ALS, 2 p.
  - Vicountess Lilian Rothermere of Harmsworth to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 24; ALS, 7 p.
  - Louis Untermeyer to Editor of Literary Review (carbon), 1921 Apr 25; TLS, 3 p.
  - Margery Swett to James Branch Cabell, w/auto. postscript, 1921 Jun 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - Lewis Worthington Smith to James Branch Cabell, 1921 May 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - S. D. Schwartz to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jul 1; TLS, 1 p.
  - Ben Moore to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - Harry Turner to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Jun; TL, 1 p.
  - Blanche Colton Williams to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 19; TLS, 1 p.
  - Horace B[risbin] Liveright to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 9; TLS, 1 p.
  - Alice MacFarland to James Branch Cabell, [1921] May 31; ALS, 4 p.
  Scrapbook 5
- Scrapbook 5, 1920-1921
  Clippings, re:
  Figures of Earth
  Chivalry
  , and
  Taboo
  , with some letters, listed below, 102 p.
  - Carl Van Doren to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 28; TLS, 1 p.
  - Alfred Kreymborg to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Mar 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - Poem, "Traveling in Private", [1921]; TMsS, 3 p.
  - Dorothea Lawrance Mann to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jun 30; TLS, 2 p.
  - Roy L. McCardell to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jul 20; TLS, 1 p.
  - Frederick B. Eddy to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jul 13; TLS, 1 p.
  - I. H. White to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jul 16; TLS, 1 p.
  - Charles H. Gabriel, Jr. to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Jul 15; TLS, 1 p.
  - Robert A. Hanson to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Aug 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - Roy L. McCardell to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Aug 22; ALS, 1 p.
  - Roy L. McCardell to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Aug 29; ALS, 1 p.
  - S[amuel] Fischer to Maurice J. Speiser, 1921 Aug 26; TLS, 1 p.
  - Maurice J. Speiser to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 13; TLS, 1 p.
  - Lewis Piaget Shanks to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Aug 31; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edward Hale Bierstadt to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Aug 9; TLS, 1 p.
  - Essay, "Literary Sore Toes," by Edward Hale Bierstadt(carbon), [1921]; TMs, 7 p.
  - A. L. S. Wood to James Branch Cabell, [1921]; TLS, 1 p.
  - Ted Le Berthon to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 8; TLS, 2 p.
  - Frank Shay to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 2; TLS, 1 p.
  - W. E. Baker to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 12; TLS, 1 p.
  - Robert C. Harper to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Nov 11; ALS, 1 p.
  - Charles E. Noyes to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Oct 18; TLS, 1 p.
  - Maurice J. Speiser to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Oct 26; TLS, 2 p.
  - John E. Lind to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 14; TLS, 2 p.
  - Alfred F. Goldsmith to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Nov 1; ALS, 1 p.
  - Carl Van Doren to James Branch Cabell, w/envelope, 1920 Oct 6; TLS, 1 p.
  - Edwin H. Shepard to Mrs. [George Steele] Seymour, 1921 Oct 3; ALS, 1 p.
  - William B. Newton to [George Steele] Seymour, w/ANS from Seymour to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Sep 24; TLS, 1 p.
  - George Steele Seymour to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Oct 11; TLS, 1 p.
  - Hettie L. Yeiser to James Branch Cabell, [1921] Oct 3; TLS, 2 p.
  - Emma Brockway Wagner to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Oct 31; ALS, 9 p.
  - M. D. Follin to James Branch Cabell, 1921 Nov 2; ALS, 1 p.